<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dan's research blog</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.halper.in/feeds/becker.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.halper.in/</id><updated>2014-10-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Data Science Incubator, Week 2</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/data-science-incubator-week-2.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Halperin</name></author><id>tag:blog.halper.in,2014-10-09:data-science-incubator-week-2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I spent today in the Data Science Incubator working with &lt;a href="http://www.astro.washington.edu/users/becker/"&gt;Andy Becker&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://github.com/uwescience/kbmod"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;KBMOD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We are trying to port the key components of the moving object detection into PostgreSQL using PostGIS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On his own, Andy designed a schema for the various data, including spatial columns and indexes. Side by side, we worked on a few issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speeding up data load: &lt;code&gt;\COPY&lt;/code&gt; is much faster than large batch insert statements, as we know.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explaining queries and seeing whether indexes are used: not yet, but the database is small so sequential scans might actually make more sense. Also, it looks like the optimizer may miss some tricks in some cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud-ification: we set up an Amazon &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RDS&lt;/span&gt; PostgreSQL+PostGIS database, and proved that we could load data in, even large data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Astro UDFs: for the kinds of spatial queries that we need, there are great C++ libraries that do all the work; we need access to those UDFs in the database! We &lt;a href="https://github.com/uwescience/kbmod/issues/1"&gt;began investigating&lt;/a&gt; PostgreSQL support for UDFs as compiled C binaries; this should be doable, but we may need to fiddle to make the C++ code play nice with PostgreSQL, which expects C…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UDFs may be a show-stopper for using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RDS&lt;/span&gt;, however — you cannot register binary UDFs there, so we will likely have to kill the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RDS&lt;/span&gt; instance and setup a manually managed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EC2&lt;/span&gt;+PostgreSQL instance instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside: Automatically-managed cloud services are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; appealing, but little implementation issues like this always seem to bite us. Similar limitations apply to Microsoft &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; Azure [no stored procedures], and Google App Engine [no CPython]—-our needs always push us into the “Sorry, you have to do &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; manually now” use case, or make us dramatically restrict the performance and capabilities of our applications. Surely this issue crops up for other users!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For next week, some preliminary goals are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;move from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RDS&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EC2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get a bigger dataset into the database, so we are in a real optimization framework&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;get the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UDF&lt;/span&gt; into the database&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work on expressing the queries and testing correctness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;optimize the indexes and queries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also chatted with &lt;a href="http://homes.cs.washington.edu/~bholt/"&gt;Brandon Holt&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://r.halper.in/coauth/bdmyers"&gt;Brandon Myers&lt;/a&gt;, and Simon Kahan about possible &lt;a href="http://grappa.io/"&gt;Grappa&lt;/a&gt;—&lt;span class="caps"&gt;KBMOD&lt;/span&gt; connections.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="becker"></category><category term="kbmod"></category><category term="incubator"></category><category term="brandon"></category><category term="grappa"></category></entry></feed>