<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dan's research blog</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.halper.in/feeds/camille.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.halper.in/</id><updated>2014-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Visualizations everywhere</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/visualizations-everywhere.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Halperin</name></author><id>tag:blog.halper.in,2014-10-10:visualizations-everywhere.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.cecs.pdx.edu/~tufte/"&gt;Kristin Tufte&lt;/a&gt; from Portland State University came to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UW&lt;/span&gt; today to visit some folks in transportation and to visit our eScience and Database groups. Most of the eScience students got to tell her about their work, and she and I discussed the Data Science Incubator and how to get undergrads involved. In her talk, she told us about S-Store, a streaming database with transactional support, and all about her work building &lt;a href="http://portal.its.pdx.edu/Portal/index.php/home/"&gt;Portal&lt;/a&gt; to manage, analyze, and visualize live traffic data on the Portland—Vancouver(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;WA&lt;/span&gt;) border in collaboration with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ODOT&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WSDOT&lt;/span&gt;, and related gov’ts. Fascinating, big, messy data problems everywhere, and great output viz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://r.halper.in/coauth/domoritz"&gt;Dominik Moritz&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; I chatted about his research on Myria’s profiler / query execution visualizer and the paper we hope to write about it this quarter. I have been logging a half-dozen ways in which the profiler has helped me debug and understand various system this summer and these use cases should help flesh out the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://r.halper.in/people/cobbc12"&gt;Camille Cobb&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; I chatted about various projects for her relating to visualization of scientific datasets. We’re doing lit review and reading up on existing work, but I think we have the gist of two interesting, novel projects to go on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my own time, I have been struggling with using &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/zzzeek/sqlalchemy"&gt;SQLAlchemy&lt;/a&gt; on Google App Engine to make Myria push work into an underlying &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DBMS&lt;/span&gt; and get much better performance on selective queries.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="tufte"></category><category term="camille"></category><category term="dominik"></category><category term="myria"></category></entry></feed>