<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dan's research blog</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.halper.in/feeds/shrainik.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.halper.in/</id><updated>2014-09-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>2014-09-24 daily</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/2014-09-24-daily.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Halperin</name></author><id>tag:blog.halper.in,2014-09-24:2014-09-24-daily.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We made final decisions about the proposed Incubator projects today. We ended up with 6 exciting projects we accepted, and 20 more we wish we could have said yes to. If your proposal was not accepted, or you want to get in touch with us some other way, note that we will be starting office hours every Thursday 9—11 in the Data Science Studio space beginning next week. (We will use Sieg 326 for the first month until construction is done).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://r.halper.in/coauth/sclayton"&gt;Sophie Clayton&lt;/a&gt; and I held a “pre-incubator” (hers was one of the chosen proposals) hack session in the afternoon, during which we wrote five or six queries to help us determine how to best co-align cytograms from different cruises and analyze the intersecting area for her research cellular diversity. It should be a fun project to continue working on this quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://homes.cs.washington.edu/~shrainik/"&gt;Shrainik Jain&lt;/a&gt; is back from Microsoft Research (where neither he nor his team was recently fired), and we chatted about his summer project and his upcoming quals project on identifying and quantifying the “high-variety” (the most important V, from my opinion) aspect of “big data”.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sophie"></category><category term="shrainik"></category><category term="incubator"></category><category term="myria"></category><category term="seaflow"></category></entry></feed>