<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dan's research blog</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.halper.in/feeds/shrainik.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.halper.in/</id><updated>2014-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Myria security, ethnography</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/posts/2014/10/15/myria-security-ethnography/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Halperin</name></author><id>tag:blog.halper.in,2014-10-15:posts/2014/10/15/myria-security-ethnography/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The newest Chrome update broke parts of &lt;a href="http://myria.cs.washington.edu"&gt;Myria&lt;/a&gt; because of new policies regarding security (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTPS&lt;/span&gt;) in web &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; calls. So, I finally did the 5 hours of work it would take to make Myria’s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; server support &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTPS&lt;/span&gt;, installed the certificate, and made all our deployment scripts. Now our users’ data (which is all publicly logged anyway) is much “safer” and, more importantly, the website works again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sat down with the ethnographers who are observing the &lt;a href="http://data.uw.edu/incubator"&gt;Data Science Incubator&lt;/a&gt; — &lt;a href="http://fioresilfvast.org/"&gt;Brittany Fiore-Silvast&lt;/a&gt; and Anissa Tanweer — to chat about the parts of the Incubator process that happened before we looped them in. We discussed the internal planning, what happened in Spring and what we wanted to change, the applicant pool, the review process, and more. It was a fun chat and merely having the chat, plus their insightful questions, made me reflect more on the process and take a step back. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://r.halper.in/coauth/billhowe"&gt;Bill Howe&lt;/a&gt; and I met with &lt;a href="http://r.halper.in/coauth/shrainik"&gt;Shrainik Jain&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://r.halper.in/coauth/domoritz"&gt;Dominik Moritz&lt;/a&gt; to discuss our project quantifying how much “variety” there is in different data systems and progress on the draft paper they have been writing. The basic idea is that we have an intuitive notion of “well-structured” databases (like the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TPC&lt;/span&gt; benchmarks), and databases with “high variety” (like SQLShare), and we ought to be able to quantitatively find differences between them. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SDSS&lt;/span&gt; should be a nice mid-point: it has many users asking potentially different questions, but their queries are limited to a well-defined, highly structured schema provided by the Skyserver team. Initial results are promising, and we are starting to put together a draft.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="britta"></category><category term="anissa"></category><category term="dominik"></category><category term="shrainik"></category><category term="bill"></category><category term="myria"></category><category term="incubator"></category><category term="variety"></category><category term="ethnography"></category></entry><entry><title>2014-09-24 daily</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/posts/2014/09/24/2014-09-24-daily/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Halperin</name></author><id>tag:blog.halper.in,2014-09-24:posts/2014/09/24/2014-09-24-daily/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We made final decisions about the proposed Incubator projects today. We ended up with 6 exciting projects we accepted, and 20 more we wish we could have said yes to. If your proposal was not accepted, or you want to get in touch with us some other way, note that we will be starting office hours every Thursday 9—11 in the Data Science Studio space beginning next week. (We will use Sieg 326 for the first month until construction is done).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://r.halper.in/coauth/sclayton"&gt;Sophie Clayton&lt;/a&gt; and I held a “pre-incubator” (hers was one of the chosen proposals) hack session in the afternoon, during which we wrote five or six queries to help us determine how to best co-align cytograms from different cruises and analyze the intersecting area for her research cellular diversity. It should be a fun project to continue working on this quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://homes.cs.washington.edu/~shrainik/"&gt;Shrainik Jain&lt;/a&gt; is back from Microsoft Research (where neither he nor his team was recently fired), and we chatted about his summer project and his upcoming quals project on identifying and quantifying the “high-variety” (the most important V, from my opinion) aspect of “big data”.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sophie"></category><category term="shrainik"></category><category term="incubator"></category><category term="myria"></category><category term="seaflow"></category></entry></feed>