<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dan's research blog</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.halper.in/feeds/software.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.halper.in/</id><updated>2014-11-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Software and databases</title><link href="http://blog.halper.in/posts/2014/11/12/software-and-databases/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-11-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Daniel Halperin</name></author><id>tag:blog.halper.in,2014-11-12:posts/2014/11/12/software-and-databases/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="/posts/2014/11/12/public-cluster-private-experiments/"&gt;today’s longer post on resource-sharing&lt;/a&gt; for what I spent most of my day thinking about — the right way to balance use of our Myria clusters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This morning, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UW&lt;/span&gt;’s software working group met to discuss our goals, recent and future interviews &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; hiring, and to organize how we respond to calls for help at the &lt;a href="mailto:info@escience.washington.edu"&gt;info@escience.washington.edu&lt;/a&gt; mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, I met with a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CS&lt;/span&gt; grad student from the &lt;a href="http://seclab.cs.washington.edu/images/banner.png"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UW&lt;/span&gt; Security Research Lab&lt;/a&gt;. He is using PostgreSQL databases to store and analyze an interesting dataset which I cannot post publicly about. We discussed database design, query authoring, using indexes properly, understanding &lt;code&gt;EXPLAIN&lt;/code&gt;ed query plans — in short, how to use databases well. Turns out that even smart, Linux-heavy grad students in computer science departments have trouble getting databases to go fast out of the box! More motivation for user-friendly services like we’re trying to put together in &lt;a href="https://sqlshare.escience.washington.edu"&gt;SQLShare&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://myria.cs.washington.edu/"&gt;Myria&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also put together a GitHub repository with the new &lt;a href="https://github.com/uwescience/branding"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UW&lt;/span&gt; eScience Institute logos&lt;/a&gt; and ordered some stickers! Drop by in 2 weeks and pick one up!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="software"></category><category term="databases"></category></entry></feed>